An Inventory of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection Records
Hoover Institution Archives
White House Conference on Child Health and Protection Records
1909-1950
XX393
White House Conference on Child Health and Protection (1930: Washington, D.C.)
150 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 scrapbook, 3 linear foot boxes 64 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The records consist of correspondence, expense statements, memoranda, pamphlets, and reports, relating to the physical and social condition of children in the United States, the status of school health education and health service programs, and proposals for the promotion of child welfare. Reports of the American Child Health Association are included.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Additional records of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection are held by the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library and the National Archives in the Washington, D.C. area. Publications of the conference may be available at libraries holding U.S. government records.
Historical Note
The White House Conference on Child Health and Protection was convened by President Herbert Hoover in Washington, D.C. on November 19-21, 1930, to raise awareness and focus public attention on issues affecting children. These conferences on children and youth were held at approximately ten-year intervals starting in 1909.
A Planning Committee was set up in July 1929 with Ray Lyman Wilbur and other individuals who were experts in their fields to work out detailed plans for a conference to "study the present status of the health and well-being of the children of the United States and its possessions; to report what is being done; to recommend what ought to be done and how to do it." Julia Lathrop, first chief of the Children's Bureau and her successor, Grace Abbott, were involved in the Planning Committee.
Recommendations of the Planning Committee prompted President Hoover to invite all interested people across the country to participate in a conference in Washington, D.C. on November 19-21, 1930, to discuss issues affecting children's lives and exchange ideas. Out of these discussions came recommendations covering prenatal care, parenting skills, education, health, and development of social skills for all children. Thirty-one volumes of information prepared by the White House conference were incorporated into a nineteen point statement and designated the Children's Charter. It carried a promise from all delegates that they would try to make it a reality.
The November conference was only the first part of President Hoover's program. The second part was to convene follow-up conferences in communities and neighborhoods where children lived. Such conferences were convened in thirty-two states, two hundred counties, and many communities, and generated public support.
The collection includes records of the American Child Health Association. It was created in 1923 out of a friendship between Herbert Hoover and Dr. L. Emmett Holt. Their plan was to integrate various volunteer organizations to make it easier to administer finances and carry out welfare programs for children. Its main focus was on education, health care, family environment, and nutrition, which they considered essential ingredients of a productive life for children. It existed until 1935.
Scope and Content of Collection
The records of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection consist of correspondence, expense statements, memoranda, pamphlets, and reports, relating to the physical and social condition of children in the United States, the status of school health education and health service programs, and proposals for the promotion of child welfare. Reports of the American Child Health Association are included.
Much of the material is organized according to the names of various committees, subcommittees, sections, and subsections. Recommendations and reports of these committees are included in the collection, many under a separate "Reports" heading. The White House conference was followed by conferences at state and local levels; records of these are organized under "Follow-up Conferences." The materials also include earlier and later records of other conferences as well as various public and private organizations.
Additional records of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection are held by the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library and the National Archives in the Washington, D.C. area. Publications of the conference may be available at libraries holding U.S. government records.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Child welfare--United States.; Child health services--United States.; School hygiene--United States.; American Child Health Association.
Container List
- American Child Health Association (A.C.H.A.) (Box 1)
  - Brochures, guide for arrangement of the files of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, memorandum, newsletter, report and test forms, and thank you note from Herbert Hoover for attending the conference, 1929-1934 and undated (Folder 1: 1)
  - Records of folders in Hoover Archives, materials transferred to Hoover War Library, and related materials, 1936-1937 and undated. (Folder 1: 2)
- American Relief Administration (A.R.A.) Children's Fund, Inc., 1929-1944. (Folder 1: 3-4)
  Correspondence between Ernest T. Attwell, Perrin C. Galpin, George A. Hastings, Inez Richardson, Edgar Rickard, R. H. Sawtelle, and Ray Lyman Wilbur; memoranda; minutes of annual meetings; note; printed matter; and telegram
- American Child Health Association (A.C.H.A.)
  - Ellen C. Babbitt, 1931-1936 and undated. (Folder 1: 5)
    Article, correspondence, and memorandum
  - Miscellany, 1930-1932. (Folder 1: 6-7)
    Mostly correspondence, but also includes clipping, memoranda, plan for White House conference magazine, press releases, program of work, and telegram
  - Helen G. Miller, 1929-1935 and undated. (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Correspondence. Includes list of national organizations, memoranda, minutes of meeting, and telegram
  - Miscellany, 1929-1936 and undated. (Folder 2: 2)
    Correspondence, financial report, list of research monographs, minutes of meeting, program, report, and telegram
- American Farm Bureau Federation, 1929-1931. (Folder 2: 3)
  Correspondence
- American Home Economics Association, 1929-1932. (Folder 2: 4)
  Clipping, correspondence, newsletter, note, and printed matter
- American Child Health Association, 1929-1933. (Folder 2: 5)
  Correspondence; list of possible attendees to the Sayville conference, Long Island, New York; newsletter; note; and program
- American Legion
  - Correspondence, note, papers, printed matter, program, and related materials, 1933-1938 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Clipping, correspondence, papers, printed matter, program, report, summary of proceedings of annual national convention, and telegram, 1929-1932 (Box-folder 3: 1)
- American Library Association, 1929-1937 and undated. (Folder 3: 2)
  Bulletin, correspondence, remarks, and telegrams
- American National Red Cross, 1929-1932. (Folder 3: 3)
  Brochure, correspondence, and miscellany
- American Dietetic Association, 1931-1932. (Folder 3: 4)
  Correspondence, newsletter, and telegram
- American Public Health Association, 1929-1932 and undated. (Folder 3: 5)
  Brochure, correspondence, list of exhibitors, report, telegram, and miscellany
- American Social Hygiene Association, 1929-1933. (Folder 3: 6)
- American associations, 1929-1944. (Folder 3: 7)
  Miscellaneous correspondence
  - A, 1929-1944 (Folder 3: 8)
  - B, 1929-1944 (Box-folder 4: 1-2)
  - C
    - Canada, 1930-1935 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Carlson, A. J., 1931 (Folder 4: 4)
    - Century Company
      - 1930-1934 (Folder 4: 5-8)
      - 1931-1950 (Box-folder 5: 1-4)
      - 1929-1932. (Folder 5: 5-7)
        Includes outline, questionnaire, report, and telegram
- Correspondence (Box 6)
  - C
    - Century of Progress, 1930-1933. (Folder 6: 1-2)
      Includes issues of Century of Progress, 1932-1933
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1935 (Folder 6: 3)
  - D
    - Dentists and dental associations, 1929-1932 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1938 (Folder 6: 5)
  - E (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1935 (Folder 7: 1)
    - Extremists
      - Medical and health, 1929-1932. (Folder 7: 2)
        Includes 1 photographic print depicting an unidentified individual, undated
      - Schools and school children, 1929-1950. (Folder 7: 3)
        Includes 1 photographic print depicting Howland township school bus, undated
      - Smoking, alcohol, and drugs, 1929-1932 (Folder 7: 4)
      - Charles H. Duncan, 1930-1934 (Folder 7: 5)
      - Labor, 1930 (Folder 7: 6)
      - HWL, 1936-1951 (Folder 7: 7)
      - Miscellaneous, 1925-1932 (Box-folder 8: 1-3)
  - F (Box 9)
    - Foreign, 1930-1936 (Folder 9: 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1937 (Folder 9: 2)
  - G
    - Guerrier, Edith, 1929-1932 (Folder 9: 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1933 (Folder 9: 4)
  - Hugo Ehrenfest and Fred J. Taussig, 1929-1931 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Obstetric education materials
    - Miscellaneous, 1932. (Folder 10: 2)
      Includes comments on reports
    - Palmer Findley and Rudolph Holmes, 1929-1932 (Folder 10: 3-4)
    - Clifford G. Grulee, J. H. M. Knox Jr., J. M. H. Rowland, Katherine Tucker, and Borden S. Veeder, 1930-1931 (Folder 10: 5)
    - George Kosmak, 1930 (Folder 10: 6)
    - Miscellaneous--Leslie B. Arey and others, 1930-1931 (Folder 10: 7)
  - H--Miscellaneous, 1929-1937 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - I
    - Institute of Public Affairs, 1931 (Folder 11: 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1934 (Folder 11: 3)
  - J--Miscellaneous, 1929-1931 (Folder 11: 4)
  - K
    - W. K. Kellogg Foundation, 1933-1936 (Folder 11: 5)
    - Kirkham, Frances W., 1929-1932 (Folder 11: 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1933 (Folder 11: 7)
  - L (Box 12)
    - Library of Congress, 1929-1932 (Folder 12: 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1933 (Folder 12: 2)
  - Mc and Mac--Miscellaneous, 1930-1934 (Folder 12: 3)
  - M
    - Master Reporting Company, 1930-1932 (Folder 12: 4)
    - Motion pictures and radio, 1929-1932 (Folder 12: 5)
    - Movies, 1932 (Folder 12: 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1933 (Folder 12: 7)
  - N (Box 13)
    - National Amateur Athletic Federation, 1929-1931 (Folder 13: 1)
    - National Catholic Organization, 1929-1932 (Folder 13: 2)
    - National Child Labor Commission, 1931-1937 (Folder 13: 3)
    - National Commission on Law Observance and Enforcement, 1931 (Folder 13: 4)
    - National Committee for Mental Hygiene, 1929-1935 (Folder 13: 5)
    - National Child Welfare Association, 1929-1933 (Folder 13: 6)
    - National Conference of Social Work, 1929-1932 (Folder 13: 7)
    - National Congress of Parents and Teachers, 1930-1938 (Folder 13: 8-10)
    - National Education Association, 1929-1933 (Folder 13: 11)
    - National Health Council, 1931-1936 (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - National Kindergarten Association, 1930-1932 (Folder 14: 2)
    - National League of Women Voters, 1929-1932 (Folder 14: 3)
    - National Metropolitan Bank, 1929-1933 (Folder 14: 4)
    - National Recreation Association, 1931-1932 (Folder 14: 5)
    - National Safety Council, 1929-1932 (Folder 14: 6)
    - National Medical Association, 1931-1932 (Folder 14: 7)
    - New York Times, 1929-1933 (Folder 14: 8)
    - National Negro Health Commission, 1929-1934 (Folder 14: 9)
    - Miscellaneous national associations, 1929-1932 (Folder 14: 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1936 (Folder 14: 11)
- Miscellaneous correspondence relating to factors and causes of fetal, newborn, and maternal morbidity and mortality, 1929-1931 (Box-folder 15: 1)
- A. J. Chesley, 1930-1931. (Folder 15: 2)
  Correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, reports, and related materials
- Proceedings of Committee B, Prenatal and Maternal Care, White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, 1931 (Folder 15: 3)
- American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology, 1931 (Folder 15: 4)
- Preliminary program and agenda of the Committee on National, State, and Local Organizations for the Handicapped, White House conference, 1930-1931 (Folder 15: 5)
- Printed matter, 1931. (Folder 15: 6)
  Official proceedings of the Section on Medical Service
- Correspondence and related materials (Box 16)
  - O--Miscellaneous, 1929-1933 (Folder 16: 1)
  - P
    - President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership, 1931-1947 (Folder 16: 2-3)
    - President's Organization on Unemployment Relief, 1931-1932 (Folder 16: 4)
    - Podiatry, 1929-1930 (Folder 16: 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1934 (Folder 16: 6)
  - R
    - Radio, 1931-1943 (Folder 16: 7)
    - W. F. Roberts, Co., 1929-1932 (Folder 16: 8)
- Clippings, 1930 and undated (Folder 16: 9)
- Correspondence and related materials (Box 17)
  - R--Miscellaneous, 1929-1933 (Folder 17: 1)
  - S
    - Social Work Publicity Council, 1931-1932 (Folder 17: 2)
    - Strauss, Joseph B. (American Citizenship Foundation), 1929-1931 (Folder 17: 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1935 (Folder 17: 4)
    - Strathmeade Corporation, 1931. (Folder 17: 5)
      Clippings
  - T--Miscellaneous, 1929-1933 (Folder 17: 6)
  - U
    - U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1929-1934 (Folder 17: 7-8)
    - U.S. Department of Commerce, 1929-1933 (Folder 17: 9)
    - U.S. Department of the Interior, 1929-1936 (Folder 17: 10)
    - U.S. Department of Justice, Bureau of Prisons, 1932 (Folder 17: 11)
    - U.S. Federal Board for Vocational Education, 1929-1931 (Folder 17: 12)
    - U.S. Department of Labor, Children's Bureau, 1929-1946 (Box-folder 18: 1)
    - U.S. Treasury Department, Public Health Service, 1930-1936 (Folder 18: 2)
    - U.S. Post Office, 1930-1934 (Folder 18: 3)
    - U.S. Superintendent of Documents, 1933-1934 (Folder 18: 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-1933 (Folder 18: 5)
  - V--Miscellaneous, 1929-1933 (Folder 18: 6)
  - W--Miscellaneous, 1929-1934 (Folder 18: 7)
  - X, Y, Z--Miscellaneous, 1929-1932 (Folder 18: 8)
  - Kosmak, George W., 1930-1941 (Folder 18: 9)
  - McCord, J. R., 1929-1931 (Folder 18: 10)
- Fred L. Adair's files (Box 19)
  - General, 1929-1933. (Folder 19: 1-6)
    Address, articles, correspondence, outline of a course on pediatrics, report, statement, survey, telegrams, and miscellany
  - Correspondence (Box 20)
    - S. M. Hamill, 1931-1932. (Folder 20: 1)
      Includes telegrams
    - Frank W. Lynch, C. Jeff Miller, Ruben Peterson, J. W. Williams, and others, 1929-1931 (Folder 20: 2)
    - John Polak and committee, 1929-1930 (Folder 20: 3-4)
    - R. D. Missey and committee, 1929-1931 (Folder 20: 5-6)
  - Notes on meeting, 1931 (Folder 20: 7)
  - Questionnaire, undated (Folder 20: 8)
- Index to filing cases, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 21: 1)
- Correspondence prior to January 1933 for filing, 1929-1933 (Folder 21: 2)
- Early organizational memoranda, 1929 (Folder 21: 3)
- Questionnaires to associations, 1929 (Folder 21: 4)
- Planning Committee records
  - Correspondence from personal files of Ray Lyman Wilbur, 1930-1935. (Folder 21: 5)
  - Correspondence, reports, and related materials, 1929-1930. (Box-folder 22: 1)
- Minutes of Planning Committee meetings, White House, 1929 July 29 (Folder 22: 2)
- Committee on Editing and Publications named by Planning Committee, 1930 (Folder 22: 3)
- Organizational memoranda after first Planning Committee meeting, undated (Folder 22: 4)
- Ray Lyman Wilbur, U.S. Department of the Interior, chairman, Planning Committee, 1929-1932. (Folder 22: 5-6)
  Relates mostly to administrative records, correspondence, and finance
- Address of Herbert Hoover--Opening session of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, 1930. (Folder 22: 7)
  Includes letters from Herbert Hoover to Ray Lyman Wilbur
- President's Committee (both Planning and Executive) (Box 23)
  - Planning Committee records, 1929-1930. (Folder 23: 1)
    Correspondence, list of members and addresses, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes, telegram, and miscellany. Includes 2 photographic prints depicting Grace Abbott, H. E. Baruard, Louis Stanley, French Strother, and Ray Lyman Wilbur, undated
  - Minutes of meeting of the Executive Committee, July 29, 1930. (Folder 23: 2)
    Includes correspondence, 1929-1930
  - Grace Abbott, 1929-1934. (Folder 23: 3)
    Article, biographical information, clippings, correspondence, notes, telegrams, and miscellany. Includes 1 photographic print depicting Abbott, undated
  - Henry Breckinridge, Planning Committee, 1929-1931. (Folder 23: 4)
    Correspondence and telegrams
  - Grace S. Burlingham, 1929-1931. (Folder 23: 5)
    Clipping, correspondence, and note
  - Bailey B. Burritt, 1929-1931. (Folder 23: 6)
  - Frederick P. Cabot, 1929-1931. (Folder 23: 7)
    Correspondence and miscellany
  - Frank Cody--Correspondence and telegram, 1929-1931. (Folder 23: 8)
    Includes 1 photographic print depicting Cody, undated
  - Ray Lyman Wilbur and Hugh S. Cumming--Personal correspondence, 1930-1932. (Folder 23: 9)
    Includes printed matter
  - James Couzens--Correspondence, 1929-1931. (Folder 23: 10)
    Includes 1 photographic print depicting Couzens, undated
  - Hugh S. Cumming, 1929-1932. (Folder 23: 11)
  - William Green--Correspondence, pamphlet, and printed matter, 1925-1932. (Folder 23: 12)
    Includes 1 photographic print depicting Green, undated
  - Lee K. Frankel--Correspondence, 1929-1931. (Folder 23: 13)
    Includes 1 photographic print depicting Frankel, undated
  - James J. Davis--Correspondence and remarks, 1928-1931. (Folder 23: 14)
    Includes 2 photographic prints depicting Davis, undated
  - Samuel McC. Hamill, 1929-1931. (Folder 23: 15)
  - S. J. Crumbine--Correspondence and telegrams, 1929-1932 and undated. (Folder 23: 16)
    Includes 2 photographic prints depicting Crumbine, undated
  - William F. King, 1929-1931. (Box-folder 24: 1)
  - Gertrude B. Lane, 1929-1932. (Folder 24: 2)
  - Julia Lathrop--Correspondence and miscellany, 1929-1932. (Folder 24: 3)
    Includes 1 photographic print depicting Lathrop, undated
  - Mrs. William Brown Maloney--Correspondence, 1929-1932. (Folder 24: 4)
    Includes 1 photographic print depicting Maloney, undated
  - Bina West Miller--Correspondence, 1929-1931. (Folder 24: 5)
    Includes 2 photographic prints depicting Miller, undated
  - Elizabeth A. Perkins--Article, correspondence, and financial records, 1929-1932. (Folder 24: 6)
    Includes 1 photographic print depicting Perkins, undated
  - Margaret Robins, 1929-1931. (Folder 24: 7)
  - Caroline Slade (Mrs. F. Louis Slade)--Correspondence and telegrams, 1929-1931. (Folder 24: 8)
    Includes 1 photographic print depicting Slade, undated
  - William F. Snow, 1929-1932. (Folder 24: 9)
  - Louise Stanley--Correspondence, press release, and note, 1929-1932. (Folder 24: 10)
    Includes 1 photographic print depicting Stanley, undated
  - French Strother, 1929 and undated. (Folder 24: 11)
- Subject Matter Committee records, 1929-1930 and undated. (Folder 24: 12-13)
  Correspondence, lists of suggested personnel and topics, memoranda, minutes of meetings, note, press release, printed matter, and telegram
- Central office records (Box 25)
  - George Barr Baker, 1929-1931. (Folder 25: 1)
  - Harry E. Barnard
    - Correspondence, clipping, financial records, printed matter, remarks, schedule, statement, and telegrams, 1929-1933. (Folder 25: 2-4)
      Includes 1 photographic print depicting Barnard, undated
    - Speeches
      - 1929 (Folder 25: 5)
      - 1930. (Folder 25: 6)
        Includes clippings
      - 1931 (Folder 25: 7)
  - William Atherton DuPuy, 1929-1939. (Box 26: 1)
    Articles, correspondence, telegrams, and miscellany
  - Theresa Dansdill, 1929. (Folder 26: 2)
  - George A. Hastings
    - Articles and manuscript preparation materials, 1932 and undated. (Folder 26: 3)
      Includes correspondence, memoranda, and printed matter
    - Correspondence, 1931-1932. (Folder 26: 4-5)
      Includes related materials
    - Newspaper and magazine correspondence, 1932 (Folder 26: 6)
    - Inter-office memoranda, 1932-1939 (Folder 26: 7)
    - Personal, 1932-1935. (Box-folder 27: 1)
      Miscellany. Includes 1 photographic print depicting Hastings, undated
    - Correspondence regarding trips and speaking engagements, 1932 (Folder 27: 2)
    - List of addresses, 1932 and undated (Folder 27: 3)
    - Monthly reports to Ray Layman Wilbur, 1932 (Folder 27: 4)
    - Press releases, 1932 and undated. (Folder 27: 5-6)
  - Inez G. Richardson
    - Correspondence, 1929-1934. (Folder 27: 7)
      Includes memoranda, notes, program, statements, telegrams, and 3 photographic prints depicting Richardson, undated
    - Article, correspondence, and program, 1930-1933 (Box-folder 28: 1)
  - Martha Van Rensselaer
    - Correspondence, 1929-1932. (Folder 28: 2-4)
    - Conference follow-up plans, 1930-1931. (Folder 28: 5)
      Includes correspondence, organizational list, and report
    - National Council of Parent Education, 1930-1932. (Folder 28: 6)
    - Speeches and articles, 1930-1931. (Folder 28: 7)
    - National organizations and education programs, 1930-1931. (Folder 28: 8)
      Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials
    - Memorial tributes--Biographical information, eulogy, letters, obituary, and program, 1932-1934. (Folder 28: 9)
      Includes 1 photographic print depicting Van Rensselaer, undated
  - George Akerson, Walter Newton, and Lawrence Richey, 1929-1932. (Folder 28: 10)
  - Herbert Hoover, 1929-1932. (Folder 28: 11)
    Address, clipping, correspondence, printed matter, and telegram
  - George A. Hastings, 1931-1932. (Box-folder 29: 1)
  - French Strother, chairman, Editorial Advisory Board
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1929-1933 (Folder 29: 2)
    - Expenses, 1930-1931. (Folder 29: 3)
      Includes correspondence
    - Public relations files, Section V
      - General, 1930 and undated. (Folder 29: 4)
      - Aida de Acosta Breckinridge, assistant director, 1930-1931 and undated. (Folder 29: 5-6)
        Articles, correspondence, list, memoranda, press release, program, statement, telegram, and miscellany
      - Press releases, 1929-1931 and undated. (Folder 29: 7-8)
        Includes clipping
  - Ray Lyman Wilbur's personal correspondence with Aida de Acosta Breckinridge and assistants in American Child Health Association regarding help with White House conference publicity, 1930-1932. (Box-folder 30: 1)
    Includes article, brochure, clipping, memoranda, note, printed matter, remarks, and telegram
  - Ray Lyman Wilbur's correspondence as chairman of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection with staff members and with central office about administrative problems, 1930-1932. (Folder 30: 2)
    Includes clipping, financial record, memoranda, program, and statement
  - Public relations and conference promotion